<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Look to it London, threatned to be fired by wilde-fire-zeal, schismatical-faction, &amp; militant-mammon. Discovered July 15. 1648. in a discourse with one Croply and Hide, by one John Dias, one of Captain Whaleys regiment, extant in a printed schedule, here verbatim inserted and commented.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81449</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1380</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E457_27</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32487</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872324</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872324</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162081</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81449)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162081)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 73:E457[27])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Look to it London, threatned to be fired by wilde-fire-zeal, schismatical-faction, &amp; militant-mammon. Discovered July 15. 1648. in a discourse with one Croply and Hide, by one John Dias, one of Captain Whaleys regiment, extant in a printed schedule, here verbatim inserted and commented.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Directed against Dias, the Levellers, and the Independents; sometimes incorrectly attributed to Dias.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 9 1648".</note>
                  <note>reproductions of originals in the Union Theological Seminary Library and the British Library. .</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Levellers --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:162081:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Look to it London, Threatned to be fired by <hi>Wilde-fire-zeal, Schiſmatical-faction, &amp; Militant-mammon.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Diſcovered July 15. 1648. in a Diſcourſe with one <hi>Croply</hi> and <hi>Hide,</hi> by one <hi>John Dias,</hi> one of Captain <hi>Whaleys</hi> Regiment: Extant in a printed Schedule, here <hi>verbatim</hi> Inſerted and Commented.</p>
            </argument>
            <head type="sub">The Preface to the Premonition.</head>
            <p>AT my firſt approach to this City out of the Country, I was ſaluted with this which <hi>Dias</hi> hath vented againſt the King, Kingdom and City; which peruſing, I was in a great ſuſpence, and my thoughts caſt in dubious ſcales what to think of it: Charity that is candid, and not raſhly credulous, cauſed me to conceit that it was but ſome meer fiction or <hi>chymera,</hi> invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like many idle Pamphlets, coined news, feigned Paſſages and Declarations, like beggars paſſports made under a hedg, and as the <hi>Piae fraudes,</hi> the lying legends of Monks and Friers, divulged by our vulgar Mercuries, to ſqueaze monies from the gulled credulities of Plebeians: withall, when I heard that ſome <hi>Catilinarians,</hi> Church and State-firebrands, did employ their Agents, as the devils working-tools, to coin and mint out of Pluto's forge lewd and loud lyes, ſcandals and ſatyrical invectives, only to ſow the ſeeds of diviſion, and caſt their Atae's brands and balls betwixt King and Parliament, camp and city, to render them ſtill in a further diſtance, I conjectured this pay-ſquib to be of that nature: ſo giving no more credit to it then to <hi>AEſops</hi> Fables, or a <hi>Canterbury</hi> tale, I ſlighted it</p>
            <p>But two days after diſcourſing with one, what he thought of the truth of it, he gave this hint, that one accidentally meeting with the Copy, printed and publiſhed it; and that there came two men, [which in probability were <hi>Croply</hi> and <hi>Hide,</hi> the ſubſcribers to it] who were very inquiſitive after the ſaid Publiſher, being in ſome paſſion that it was divulged without their conſent; adding withal, that he need not to have printed it in corners, nor to have vented it in hugger-mugger; ſince all the paſſages in it were true, as they would confirm by their oaths: This paſſage gave me ſome light into
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:162081:2"/>
the reallity of it, and was ſome inducement unto me, to think it was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together fabulous. Yet, notwithſtanding all this, my charity was of ſo large a ſize, that I thought it was but one Doctor <hi>Dulmans</hi> opinion, the <hi>Ignis Fatuus,</hi> or <hi>Brutum Fulmen</hi> of one Bragadochian ſoldier; the fools bolt ſoon ſhot, of one <hi>John Dias,</hi> whoſe tongue ran wrong Bias. Hence I thought it as unworthy of my genius to anſwer it, as for an Eagle to ſtoop to a Fly, or an Elephant to a Mouſe: but beſides the urgings and ſollicitings of ſome judicious friends, who ſpur'd me on to give ſome critical obſervations of the fiery and factious paſſages in this ſpleenitive and zeal-drunk diſcourſe: hoping the beſt, that the moſt and the beſt in the Army had neither head, hand, nor heart in theſe deſtructive Menaces ſprinkled now in Print: yet fearing the worſt, that this <hi>Di-aſs</hi> in <hi>preſenti,</hi> had ſome birds in the Army of his own bloody feather, who ſung his notes; (in which I was the more grounded by paralelling the particulars here with ſome things in this nature which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Martialiſts vented even to my ſelf not many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> As alſo knowing that oft a man may know by the Market-folk how the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket rules; and that the nature of many wolves may be ſeen in one: ſince alſo <hi>abundans cautela non nocet,</hi> abundant circumſpection never did hurt; no more then preventing phyſick againſt a feared diſeaſe: I thought good by a warning peece with pouder, ere the threatned bullet be felt, or the match, fire and ſalt-peter unſavorily finelt, to awaken ſecure <hi>Troynovant</hi> to a cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telous watching of their own <hi>Sinons</hi> within them, confederate with armed Greeks without, ere the flames be kindled in their houſes, which here break as a ſulphureous Aetna out of the mouth of this Mounſier Malignant, whoſe tongue, fired by Hell, is a world of wickedneſs. Hereupon, <hi>ex tempore,</hi> as the Printer can depoſe, without any other book or manuſcript then a naked room, in a declarative deſcant on this plain and vain ſong, I porcupined my pen to run at Tilt with this <hi>Junior Donquixot,</hi> this City-firing <hi>orlando furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſo,</hi> acting the parts here on a paper-ſtage of an <hi>Hercules ſurens,</hi> and mad <hi>Ajax,</hi> or at leaſt of Sir <hi>Henry Hotspur,</hi> and Sir <hi>Ferdinando Flaſh,</hi> who here vents his mind with his wind: which windy bladder I thus pen-prick in this ſubſequent ſynopſis, and ſurvey of every black and bloody word in his mouths ſhop, from the warehouſe of his Canniballized heart.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he declared, The Reſolution of the Army was to fight for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[The Reſolution.</hi>] Its an excellent ſpirit to be reſolute in a good cauſe: as <hi>Daniel</hi> reſolved not to pollute himſelf with the Kings meat; <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> not to bow to the Kings image, more then ſome <hi>ex moliori luto;</hi> that would not ſo much as bow to an Engliſh Baal, an Altar. So <hi>Luther</hi> is reſolute to go to <hi>Wormes,</hi> if every tile on their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:162081:2"/>
were a devil; though he ſhould ſuffer as much as <hi>Jerom</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> and <hi>John Huſs</hi> at the inconſtant Counſel at <hi>Conſtance.</hi> But to be reſolute in a bad cauſe, like ſome Popiſh Pſeudomartyrs, and the <hi>French Byron,</hi> whoſe great ſpirit would not ſubmit to the mercy of the French King, no more then <hi>Cato</hi> of <hi>Vtica</hi> to <hi>Caeſars</hi> pardon; or <hi>Cleopatra</hi> to grace <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his triumph: this ſavors either of ſwoln pride, or perverſe ſelf-will, or main folly, and childiſh ſimplicity to hold a candle in the hand till it burn the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; or a hardy waſp till ſhe ſting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[To fight for themſelves:</hi>] In which though many acute and naſuted Criticks are not deceived, thinking no better of it at the firſt then <hi>Noah</hi> of his ſon, <hi>nec de eo melius ſperavi;</hi> yet many that did conſide more in them, that they had fought like ſecond <hi>Joſhuahs,</hi> and <hi>Gideons,</hi> and <hi>Davids,</hi> and <hi>Jonathans,</hi> the Lords battels, and not their own, at leaſt like the beſt Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Patriots, <hi>pro aris &amp; focis,</hi> for Religion and the peace and ſafety of the Kingdom, reading now that all their ſtreams run homeward for themſelves and their own ends, they cry <hi>quant â de ſpe, de re decidi,</hi> we are ſouly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in them: if it be true (as perhaps it is not) which this ſoul mouth blat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but I hope they do not, <hi>dare verba (et verbera,</hi>) feed us as fools and children with fair words, and delude us as <hi>Zeuxis</hi> deluded hungry birds with painted grapes; or as <hi>Faustus</hi> and <hi>Apollonius</hi> their gueſts with painted diſhes: if it proves thus, all is not gold that gliſters: and in mens hearts are many odd corners (againſt all that ſhould oppoſe them) whether King, Parliament, Church, State, Senate, Synod, or God-himſelf. I ſcarce beleeve they be ſuch <hi>Junior Caeſars</hi> with Romanized Reſolves, and their <hi>Facta eſt alea,</hi> to hoyſt fails againſt all ſurging waves: or ſecond <hi>Hannibals,</hi> to cut the ways to their own ends through Flints and Rocks with fire and vinegar; yea to cut with <hi>Alexanders</hi> ſword all Gordian knots of difficulties and dangers; though I know withall how virulent and violent ſelf-love is, and ſelf-will, how head-ſtrong boiling paſſions and perturbations, like <hi>Bellero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phons</hi> horſes unbridled with <hi>Minerva's</hi> bit, of ſollid wiſdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[They reſolved not to be governed by a King:</hi>] No more did thoſe ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> who deſpiſed <hi>Saul,</hi> and brought him no preſents, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. nor thoſe that ſaid, <hi>To your Tents, O Iſrael, what have we to do with the ſon of Jeſſe,</hi> 2 Sam. 20. Nor thoſe in the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Let us break their bonds and caſt their cords from us,</hi> whom the King of <hi>Sion</hi> threatens to cruſh as a potters veſſel, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Not to be governed]</hi> Kit after kind, its natural for all, both birds, bruites and beaſts, as well as wilde men, to deſire licentious liberty; (like Popery and frenzy) it runs in a blood: 2. withall they ſympathize with their predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude;</hi> theſe makers of Sects <hi>ſpeak evil of dignities
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:162081:3"/>
and despiſe government.</hi> The devil is <hi>ſemper idem,</hi> no changeling in his ways and ends, he acts ſtill the ſame parts in all ages, only the ſceans, ſtage, and perſons being changed: he hath had always his Levellers, who made no difference betwixt high and low, ſuperior and inferior in Church and State, who have villified, yea nulled both <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, and have pleaded for, and practiſed an Anarchy, an Ataxy, a Platonical and an Anabaptiſtical community. Oh this government! how degenerate and unregenerate Nature ſnuffs at it, as the wilde Onager in <hi>Job</hi> ſnuffs up the wind! how every mad colt wrathfully champs the curb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bit, and would caſt his rider! how glad would the frogs be rid of their ſtorks, that theymight croak what poyſond ſtuff they pleaſed, in every corner</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Not to be governed by a King,</hi>] But like the <hi>Arabians</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> and the <hi>Nomades,</hi> and the <hi>Troglodites,</hi> and thoſe about Mount <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> to wander, and rave, and rake, and ramble, and ſcramble at pleaſure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controu: for had they a King they could not lick their fingers, nor fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their ſilver wings, nor build their neſts on high, nor ſet up a <hi>Dagon,</hi> a <hi>morſtrum horrendum,</hi> a hotch-potch of all Religions, call'd Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, for the <hi>Turks Alcaron,</hi> the <hi>Jewiſh Thalmud,</hi> the <hi>Papal Miter</hi> and <hi>Maſs,</hi> yea for <hi>Simon Magus</hi> and his <hi>Hellena, Montanus</hi> and his <hi>Priſcilla;</hi> for <hi>Bohemian naked Adamites, Belgick Familiſts</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſts, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane David Georgians, Arminians, Photinians,</hi> and who not, even <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque vult,</hi> as likely to agree together in one Land, as ſo many cocks in one pit, or the heads of the ſerpent <hi>Amphiſbena,</hi> one fighting againſt another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[No King,</hi>] But an <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> or <hi>Democracy</hi> of that beaſt with many heads, the multitude, (ruling at beſt by their Tribunes:) no Monarchy, no King, which all Nations, as well as the <hi>Iſraclites,</hi> have ever deſired; yea, which the bees ſubject themſelves unto in their <hi>Amazonian</hi> and <hi>Platonical Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[No King,] Oh quam multos Dominos habet qui unum non habet:</hi> how many Kings ſhall we have, if not one King! In a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Tyranny, every luſt will be a Lord Dane; every Sect, Schiſm and Hereſie, a domineering King: as when there was no King in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> every man will beleeve, ſay, and do, <hi>ad libitum &amp; placitum,</hi> what he pleaſeth: the ſtrongeſt, like birds and beaſts of prey, feed on the weakeſt; as <hi>Pikes</hi> in a pond on the leſſer Fry: But if their Reſolution be (as the preſent acts of their Leaders and Governors now ſpeak their intentions) that they will have no evil-counſelled King, ſpurd on at this inſtant, without any modification, by his <hi>Junior Achitophels and Court-Hamans;</hi> as a Lion grated, batted, and incenſed, with a wrathful paw, to tear his beſt Patriots, and all that have oppoſed, not him, but his ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counſelled late poſtures and paſſages: If they deſire the Lion ſpur'd on to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162081:3"/>
rampant, to be piouſly patient and paſſant: and ſo making an Act of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion of <hi>real</hi> or <hi>imaginary affronts,</hi> writ in duſt, or drowned in <hi>Leth,</hi> to rule meerly for and not againſt the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah;</hi> in this we ſhall be ſtill more beholden to the (formerly well improved) pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, proweſs, and piety of the General, &amp; his worthieſt Commilitones, not regarding the brayings of this dull Aſs, and of ſome other leſſer blatrant Beaſts of the <hi>Forreſt,</hi> who would have the Lion ſtil in his grate, and to be no King: as if the Heavens and our Horizon ſhould have no ſun, and the body ſhould be Cyclopical, and Polyphemiz'd without eyes, yea without a head.</p>
            <p>And that nothing vexed them more then the Parl'aments recalling their Declarations of making no more Addreſſes to the King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vexed them more.</hi>] Good men are vexed with the ſins and ſufferings of themſelves, and of others, as was <hi>David,</hi> Pſalm 119. <hi>Lot,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> Chap. 9. 1. and others: but to be vext for well doing, and to be <hi>enraged,</hi> as <hi>Unicorns</hi> and <hi>Turkicocks,</hi> at the fight of <hi>red Stammels,</hi> at what is legal, or will admit of a good <hi>conſtruction,</hi> is, for men to fight with their own ſhadows, or as <hi>Donquixot</hi> with Rams, and windmils for <hi>Gyants,</hi> or as inraged <hi>Ajax</hi> with <hi>heards</hi> of ſheep, for <hi>Uliſſes:</hi> Vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and <hi>ſorrow</hi> be good for nothing but ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Parliaments recalling their Declarations.</hi>] Is not he well ſtudyed in the Statutes, that knows not how many <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Acts have been repealed in every Kings Raign? 2. Are their acts like the <hi>decrees</hi> of the <hi>Medes and Perſians;</hi> yea, as Gods <hi>decree,</hi> not to be <hi>recalled.</hi> 3. Have not the learnedeſt Synods and Councels <hi>erred?</hi> As that of <hi>Lateran,</hi> of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> and lately at <hi>Trent,</hi> with many moe? are all Councels with theſe four which S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſo honored, to be equalized with the four E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts? 4. Are our <hi>Patritians</hi> Gods or Angels? are they not men? and ſo ſubjected, <hi>errare, decipi,</hi> to humane frailties, like <hi>Elias, lames</hi> 5? may they not <hi>humani aliquld pati,</hi> as well as the beſt of meer men, be in ſome things <hi>erroneous,</hi> as the clear Sun and Moon are ſubjected to their cloudings and eclipſings? 5. Is not an inconvenience better then a miſchief? better to recal an <hi>Error,</hi> then to perſiſt in it: better to be <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metheus,</hi> afterwiſe, then not wiſe, ſince <hi>errare humanum, preſerverare dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicum,</hi> at all? as its ſaid of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> that they are wiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards; and of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> wiſe before: yet beg him for a fool that is wiſe, neither before nor after, that like him who hath bad cards, and bad caſting at dice, (which is now a high Courts Caſe,) doth not help it as he may in after-play.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Though Inconſtancy, to weave and unweave, like <hi>Penelope,</hi> to act and react, and recall, be a brand or a blot in many men of great parts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162081:4"/>
and great ſpirits, changing their minds every day, as <hi>Nero</hi> his ſuits, as though they were nought but changeable taffaty; yet may not wiſe men change their Reſolutions, as <hi>David</hi> did, reſolving to march againſt <hi>Nabal, 1 Sam.</hi> 25. as Hares and Hedghogs change their forms, as the winds of croſs occaſions blow? If I reſolve a journey, yet being inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that there is <hi>Leo in via,</hi> a Lyon in the way, a <hi>French Aſſaſſinate, Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Bandetties,</hi> or a plundering <hi>Nimrodian,</hi> to cut my throat for my purſe, may I not recall my reſolves for travelling that way?</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>Felix qui potuit rerum cognoſcere cauſas,</hi> Can the wiſeſt man foreſee the iſſues and events of all good cauſes? Whether preaching will ſoften a <hi>Joſiah</hi> like wax, or Sunlike obdurate a <hi>Pharaoh</hi> like clay, for breaking; as <hi>ex malis moribus bonae leges,</hi> good Laws proceed from evil manners: ſo who knows what evil conſequences may come of good acts, like bad ſtomacks, which turn good meat into evil humours?</p>
            <p>Eightly, As <hi>David</hi> himſelf ſaid, he was in a great ſtrait, 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 24. the beſt and wiſeſt of men may ſometimes be in ſuch ſtraits, ſo ſail be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Caribdis,</hi> two contrary Rocks, that all their wit and policy cannot evade their daſhing, if not ſplitting, yea oft ſhipwracking, of credit, conſcience, or both: The body Political, (like the body natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, labouring of a dropſie, and a yellow or black Jaundice both at once, from contrary cauſes,) may be ſo diverſifiedly diſeaſed, that the beſt ſtate-Phyſitian knows not how to cure the one, but he indangers killing, by increaſing the other, the ſalve proving alſo oft more dangerous then the fore; as to him who cut off his toes to cure the raging Gout: All theſe may be applyed to <hi>Parliamentary Actings,</hi> and <hi>reactings,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealings,</hi> ſo oft; like <hi>Mariners,</hi> now hoiſting up ſails in calms, preſent or hoped, now pulling them down, yea cutting down the main maſt, and every man pumping for life, in tempeſtuous ſtorms.</p>
            <p>And being asked, why they did not declare, he anſwered, that yet it was no time.</p>
            <p>No time,] <hi>Omne tempus habet,</hi> Every thing hath a time for mirth, or for mourning, for ſolace, or ſorrow, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3. only there is no time for ſinning; which like ſnow in <hi>June,</hi> and rain in Harveſt, is ſtill out of time, and as harſh muſick out of tune too; though every time is not fit for every truth to be brosched, (as pearls unfit for ſwine, and holy things for dogs,) yet there is not time for <hi>Guſmans cheats,</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitical Equivocations,</hi> or for <hi>Judas</hi> his <hi>treacherous kiſs,</hi> or <hi>Joabs</hi> imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſtab; no time to be watched for miſchief, as <hi>Wolves</hi> and <hi>Lyons</hi> for their <hi>preys:</hi> And indeed this wrtching a time, for baſe or bloody ends, favours ſtrongly of an <hi>Eſaus</hi> ſpirit, who plumps and fats his ſpleen
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:162081:4"/>
with the hoped time of his Fathers death, &amp; then he wil wreak his wrath on his ſupplanting Brother, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. and on <hi>Cain,</hi> the murtherers ſpirit, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 13. who watcht his time to butcher innocent <hi>Abell, Gen.</hi> 4. Yea, it ſympathizeth with all wicked ones, who watch their times (as the Adulterer the twi-light, the ſilent Serpent his opportunity to ſting, and the birding Cat the buſhed ſparrow,) how to execute their peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent deviſes: as the <hi>Papiſt s</hi> hoped a time, after the death of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> that all would be their own; then up <hi>Moah,</hi> and to the ſpoil: In the mean time, <hi>rebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> as the caſe ſtood, they have liberty of conſcience from the <hi>Pope</hi> (the only <hi>Monopolizer</hi> of that <hi>Mungril,</hi>) to be religious <hi>Hermaphrodites, Papiſts, Proteſtants,</hi> either, or neither, as ſtood beſt for their own ends, by <hi>pens, pikes, fires,</hi> or <hi>faggots:</hi> See your faces in the glaſſe of that Tyrant, that lies lutking, and couchant for a time, to be rampant. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Shortly, he did not doubt but all would be their own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shortly.</hi>] This ſhort-lye may prove a ſhort or a long lye: as ſome ſluggiſh ſervants preſently, oft proves a preſent lye; as Chriſts Fleſh held really in the Sacrament by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> is a reall-lye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shortly.</hi>] How his lips water at the golden prey, which he, and ſuch as he, have gulpht down and devoured in their hopes, as the Foxes lips water at the grapes and pullein, and the Cats at the fiſh, which they have not yet catcht; and indeed (as when the <hi>Pope</hi> gave <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>Tyrone,</hi>) if he could conquer it, all the craft is in the catching; win gold and wear it: But as a long man ſaid of a ſhort cloak which he borrwoed, he would make it long enough ere he reſtored it; ſo this fellow, that is one of the <hi>Haſtings,</hi> in his hot <hi>deſires,</hi> may perhaps dance attendance long enough, and cool his toes, like the ſchriech-owl, ere he ſee them effected; his muſick with ſilver ſtrings may be ſo long in tuning, as may turn him all into frets, for all his ſhortlye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He did not doubt.</hi>] Indeed the ſtrongeſt faith, even of an <hi>Abraham,</hi> a <hi>Sarah, Gen.</hi> 17. a <hi>Zachariah, Luke</hi> 1. a <hi>David,</hi> when he diſſembled a madneſs, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. a <hi>Thomas Didimus, Iohn</hi> 20. and of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles themſelves, hath been mixt with doubtings; as cold with heat in luke-warm water, and darkneſs with light, in the twilight; which doubting is like ſore lips in a ſickneſſe; a bad thing in it ſelf, yet a good ſign of health; and its the ſtrongeſt faith that reſts and confides in God, in the greateſt exigents, as did <hi>Abraham,</hi> hoping againſt hope, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. and <hi>Aſa,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. and <hi>Iehoſophat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. and <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30. 6. But to be confident in evil, as <hi>Witches, Conjuerers,</hi> and <hi>Necromancers,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:162081:5"/>
give the Devil a faith, who, is Gods Ape, promiſeth them his aſſiſtance; and as the Collier was wiſht to give the Romiſh Church an implicite faith, and to pin his ſoul on the <hi>Popes</hi> ſleeve, to carry it to Heaven or to Hell: This bold and brazen-faced folly and preſumption builds but as on an Iriſh Bog, and ditcheth the ſoul in the loweſt Hell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He did not doubt but all would be their own.</hi>] But, <hi>festina lente,</hi> he may firſt faſt all the turkiſh <hi>Lents,</hi> ere he feaſt in <hi>Apollos</hi> with a <hi>Lucullus.</hi> Curſt Cows have ſhort horns: <hi>Iezabel</hi> did not doubt but to take off the head of <hi>Elias,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. but the dogs ſhall firſt eat her for Carrion: <hi>Benhadab</hi> in his drink doubts not but to take the forces of <hi>Iſrael</hi> alive, but his hopes were ſtrangled in theſe Halters, which his Courtiers wore about their necks, as their beſt Tiffany. 1 <hi>Kings 20. Saul</hi> doubts not but to take <hi>David</hi> intrentcht, as in a trap, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. And that railing <hi>Rabſhekah,</hi> and blaſphemous <hi>Senacherib,</hi> doubt not but to ſwallow up <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and his people, as the Whale did <hi>Ionas;</hi> but God had a hook in both their <hi>noſes, 2 Kings 19. Goliah</hi> doubts not but to give <hi>Davids</hi> fleſh to the fowls of the ayr, but <hi>David,</hi> with a ſlinged ſtone, daſheth all theſe hopes, with his brains out of his fooliſh head, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. So the <hi>Spaniſh Armado,</hi> in the year 88, chriſtened invincible, by the <hi>Nun</hi> of <hi>Liſbon,</hi> (the Devil being the God-father, and Pride the God-mother,) hoped to make <hi>England a Chaos</hi> of confuſion; and <hi>Ferneſius</hi> the Prince of <hi>Perma</hi> doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not but to ride his horſe up to the ſaddle in the blood of the <hi>Luther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> but God ſo ſought for the <hi>Protestants,</hi> yea the <hi>winds</hi> and the <hi>waves,</hi> as once for <hi>Honorius,</hi> as the Red Sea once againſt <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the <hi>Stars,</hi> and the River <hi>Kiſhon</hi> againſt <hi>Siſera,</hi> haliſtones from Heaven againſt the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malakites,</hi> and Hornets againſt the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> that all theſe felt and found what it was to fight againſt God, to kick againſt the prick, and to reckon without their Hoſt, as this fond <hi>Braggadocheo</hi> ſells the Fox skin before he be catcht, and reckons his chickens before they be harcht.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All would be their own.</hi>] All their own? What will not part ſerve? as ſome Gentleman pay their debts, by a kind of Synecdoche, cal'd <hi>pars pro toto,</hi> a part for the whole; will he and his outſtrip the Pope, that great <hi>Participle,</hi> who takes part from the <hi>Clergy,</hi> part from the <hi>Secular,</hi> and part from both? Will theſe <hi>Harpies</hi> play ſweep-ſtake, and take all, both ſtock and thwatch, harveſt and gleanings; all from <hi>Courts, Carts,</hi> and <hi>Crown;</hi> from <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> from <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State?</hi> All? both <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Government, Power</hi> and <hi>Pelf;</hi> Will they as <hi>Cormorants</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour all before them? as the <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> when they over ran <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Lumbardy;</hi> will they ſwallow up all as flap <hi>Dragons?</hi> Gods part and all? Will they rob <hi>Altars</hi> make with <hi>Pompey</hi> Temples
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:162081:5"/>
Stables for Horſes? ſhave off <hi>Eſculapius</hi> golden beard: reave the <hi>Tholous</hi> gold: rake not only (as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> with the <hi>Indians,</hi> and the <hi>Romans</hi> with the <hi>Iews)</hi> into the guts of the living; but as <hi>Darius,</hi> once, into the ſepulchres of the dead for gold: Oh will theſe Catepillers eat all the green things of the Land, as the Aegyptian Locuſts, called Monks and Fryers oft in this our <hi>Albion,</hi> our <hi>Terra florida:</hi> Will they monopolize all? and leave neither the Clergies part, the tenth; nor the widows part, the thirds. Will they rob the ſpittle and ſhear the Ape? Will they make a mad medley of the dogs hair and the wool of a <hi>Baboon?</hi> Oh, ſure, however ſuch as are the botts and glaunders in the Army, the <hi>Achans</hi> in the Camp, ſeed on ſuch baſe and ſordid projects, as <hi>Scarabean</hi> fleas on dunghils; who mayfor all their gaping jaws miſs their fat morſels, as <hi>Aeſops</hi> dog miſt the ſubſtance for a ſnatched ſhadow; and as <hi>Ixion</hi> imbraced a Cloud for <hi>Iuno;</hi> their brag being a good dog, yet catching nothing: yet I am perſwaded, the noble and gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirits in the Army, yea ſtill in my old phraſe the beſt and the moſt, are as far from ſuch dunghil thoughts, and from ſtooping to ſuch baſe Lures, that if Satan or his organs did but dart them into their hearts, they would pump them out again, as Mariners waters out of their ſhips; yea caſt them out as new wines poyſon out of the barrels, and the ſeas their froth to the ſhores: God forbid we ſhould condemn all the Diſciples for ſome <hi>Iudaſſes:</hi> or all profeſſors for ſome <hi>Anani-aſſes</hi> and <hi>Sapphiraes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtill to follow them and to overtake them as the Hound the Fox in ſlow running: Commeating further; <hi>[That if the Army ſhould thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, the City and Kingdom would riſe]</hi> as <hi>Dias</hi> was told.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Would riſe,</hi>] Elſe they had an <hi>aſinine</hi> patience; a ſleepiſh ſimplicity without any mixture of ſerpentine calidity, to lie ſtil in a ditch til the ravens pluck their pelts, and pulld out their eyes; yea their right eyes, as <hi>Naaſh</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> projected to thoſe of <hi>Iabes Gilead,</hi> 1 Sam. 11. ſince nature teacheth the worm turn again if ſhe be trod on, the crows to chatter, and wrens to wrangle if their neſts be pulld down; elſe where were the old Engliſh valor, if cowed and over-awed (as the <hi>Britains</hi> once) with a Daniſh, a Popiſh, an Aegyptian yoke: ſome being fit to be abuſed, yea to ſleep to <hi>Mecanas,</hi> like a ſawning Courtier, a timerous Traveller, and a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riatized odcomb, to receive injuries and give thanks; but an Engliſh-man, rightly bred, is not fit to be abuſed: though a grated Lion may perhaps be pluckt by the beard, yet its dangerous to anger his whelps abroad, and to provoke them too far, if by any fair and ſquare way of Truce or Treaty they may be appeaſed. <hi>[He anſwered,] Anſer</hi> is Latin for a Gooſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[They regarded not the City,</hi>] But the City hath both regarded and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded them; and is ſhe now ſhaken off, as the ſpaniel ſhakes off the water
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:162081:6"/>
when he hath uſed it to ſwim to his deſired duck? Have they climbed their own ends by her, and will they now throw her by like broken Ladders? Have they no more need of her men, nor of her moneys? (the nerves and ſinews of War.) Nor of her Ammunition which they carry away in Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loads full of kindneſs? even many a man that makes Matrimony a matter of money, regards the ſilver feathers, if not the fleſh of the bird which he takes into his neſt: but this is not <hi>commune malum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[But could fire it at pleaſure,</hi>] At pleaſure: Oh Gunpowder ſpirits, Jeſuited <hi>Ignatians,</hi> who would conclude all in <hi>ferio, in ferro &amp; flamma:</hi> as the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> inquiſition, and <hi>Bonner</hi> once, and <hi>Gardner</hi> (all are not guilty of this: thoſe who are gracious in the Army are alſo grateful,) in their invincible arguments of fire and faggot: When <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> would have fetcht fire from heaven to burn the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> Chriſt told them they knew not of what ſpirit they were, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9. But without being at coſt with a. <hi>Herald,</hi> we may derive ſome ſpirits from the torrid <hi>Zone;</hi> from the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree and hot line of <hi>Thais,</hi> that hot harlotrcauſing <hi>Alexander</hi> to burn <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſepolis;</hi> of the mad <hi>Greeks</hi> firing <hi>Troy</hi> (fired firſt by the luſt of <hi>Paris;</hi>) of <hi>Nero</hi> firing <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſinging funeral Elegies to it, as to ſecond <hi>Troy;</hi> of the <hi>Tartars</hi> firing the great city <hi>Moſco;</hi> of <hi>Faux</hi> the firebrand (in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh intention and invention) of a Parliament. But to proceed where they exceed, <hi>[Fire the City,</hi>] Alas its fired already! Firſt, by wilde fire Sects and Schiſms, flaming like a ſulphureous Aetna, unquenchable as the coals of Jumper, yea wel nigh as hell-fire, either by the milk of the Word, or the waters of the ſanctuary, ſtill fuellized by zealous ignorance and arrogance: the diviſions of <hi>Reuben</hi> being great thoughts of heart, <hi>Iudges</hi> 5. Moſt blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sectaries, rather breaking like Oaks (chiefly Hereticks, like <hi>Arrius, Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Anaſtaſius, Valens, Marcion, Manes,</hi> and others, who all came to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical ends,) then bowing like Reeds, ſhutting their eyes againſt the Sun of truth. Secondly, fired by wilde-fire wrath and ſpleen, burning and raging inwardly, like fire cloſe ſmothered, in divided hearts, breaking out into fiery factions and fractions in houſes and families amongſt thoſe that are neereſt united in the bonds of blood, marriage, nature, conſanguinity and affinity.</p>
            <p>Withall the phraſe of firing the City, makes me ſtart back, as <hi>Moſes</hi> from his rod turn'd ſerpent, makes my hand ſtupid, <hi>et vox faucibus haret,</hi> and my tongue ſpeechleſs, as if I had ſeen a fiery-eyed Wolf, and it ſpeaks de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratively to me, that there is no ſin ſo groſs, ſo grievous, ſo hainous, ſo horrible, but a graceleſs and godleſs man, an unregenerate man out of Chriſt may commit it. The murthering not only of a brother, with <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom,</hi> but of a mother as <hi>Nero</hi> did <hi>Agrippina:</hi> the killing of a father per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated by the two ſons of <hi>Senacherib, 2 King.</hi> 19. the impriſoning of a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162081:6"/>
father, as the Duke of <hi>Geldria</hi> his aged Sire: Rebellion againſt a father as <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> againſt <hi>David;</hi> murthering of their own children, as did <hi>Manlius Brutus, Progne</hi> and <hi>Medea:</hi> Firing of Temples, as <hi>Eroſtratus</hi> the Temple of <hi>Diana:</hi> Aſſaſſinating Kings, as <hi>Ravillack</hi> and <hi>Jaques Clemens,</hi> the two <hi>French Henries:</hi> ripping up the bowels of women with child, as <hi>Hazael,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8. and our <hi>Iriſh Rebels:</hi> yea roſting ſome at lingring fires, as the ſame Rebels did Mr <hi>Watſon</hi> a Preacher: and here, as you ſee, ſome threatning to fire one of the moſt glorious Cities in Chriſtendom: what worſe acts could the <hi>Sodomites</hi> do if they were here on earth: yea what worſe could the devil himſelf do, if he were viſibly in the ſhape of man?</p>
            <p>Withal ſee this ſurious ſin of Firing aggravated, <hi>cui bono,</hi> to what end, what good doth it but only to fuellize revenge, which the <hi>Italians</hi> make the ſweeteſt thing tinder the Sun, as in that fiery faction in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> betwixt <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Jehochonan,</hi> in damnable ſpleen they fired a magazine of 20 years proviſion of corn, only to plague the City and themſelves, conquered by this means by the belly more then the blade: ſo <hi>homo homini lupus &amp; demon,</hi> one man ſo is a wolf, yea a devil to another, in doing miſchief only, and doing themſelves no good, againſt the dictate both of Reaſon and Religion.</p>
            <p>Moreover conſider this fellows phraſe, <hi>in firing the City at pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[At pleaſure,</hi>] Oh the further aggravation of ſin! its pleaſure to a carnal heart, as carrion to a dog or vulture, mire to a ſwine, and filthy mud to a frog: that which is the ſorrow and vexation of a gracious heart, to a combating <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7. to a mournful <hi>Jeremy</hi> throughout his <hi>Lamentations,</hi> yea to a tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted <hi>David, Pſa. 6. &amp;</hi> 38. is a pleaſure and a paſtime to a graceleſs wretch; even as <hi>Sampſon</hi> a holy <hi>Nuzarite</hi> is a mocking-ſtock to the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> Judg. 16 <hi>Iſaac</hi> to <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Iſmael, Gen.</hi> 21. Holy <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Michal,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. <hi>Lot</hi> to the <hi>Sodomites, Gen.</hi> 19. <hi>Paul</hi> as a babler to the <hi>Athenians, Act.</hi> 19. and Chriſt himſelf both in his Sermons and Sufferings to the carnal <hi>Jews, Mat. 19. &amp;c.</hi> 27. Yea here you ſee is a paſquil mad-cap that joyns the firing of a City and pleaſure both in oneline: as if he would warm his hands in the flaming, as now his heart in the conceited kindling of ſuch a fire. But its a paſtime to a fool to do miſchief, and the ſeat of the ſcorner being height of ſin, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 1. 1. there wants nothing but a cuſhion to that ſeat, which is damnation, unleſs ſpeedy converſion prevent ſubverſion. Laſtly, <hi>premoniti premuniti,</hi> forewarned, let <hi>Troynovant</hi> be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed, to be cautelous, to take heed how ſhe entertains or retains any ſuch brands into her City as would burn her: any ſuch hotſpurs (though blind and bloody Zealots) as would fire her: any ſuch ſnakes into her boſom as would deadly ſting her: any ſuch mice into her bowels as would deſtroy her: in plain terms, if ſhe diſcover let her diſcard any ſuch ſpirit or ſpirits as would betray her, as <hi>Zopirus</hi> did <hi>Babylon, Sinon Troy, York Devoutree</hi> to the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> for my part had
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162081:7"/>
I but a ſuſpition of ſuch a ſojourner in my houſe as would cut my throat or my child's, or any way by treachery abuſe me, as <hi>Paris</hi> did <hi>Menalaus;</hi> or by cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as the two young <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> the daughter of <hi>Schedaſus,</hi> they ſhould not neſtle under my rooſe one night longer: But in this caſe I preſcribe nothing, for that were to teach Eagles to fly and Dolphins to ſwim; the City is ſo punctually wiſe, even by experiments. I need not light my candle to their ſun: withal far be it from me to put any jealouſies and panick fears into their heads and hearts, either of the fame-worthy General, whoſe actions have hitherto ſpoke him both juſt and noble, or of the Army in general, who were fair-conditioned even when the ball was at their foot to have pludered with more opportunity then perhaps they may have again; yea and with more power too as poſſeſſors of the <hi>Tower.</hi> But when I conſider again the <hi>fearful Tragedies in Antioch, Gaza, Alexandria, Olyſcopon,</hi> and elſ where, yea in <hi>Belgia,</hi> in the <hi>Rustick Wars</hi> of <hi>Munſtsr,</hi> and <hi>John à Leiden,</hi> which have been acted and writ by Hiſtorians rather with blood then ink, by blind zeal, bloody <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> and <hi>factious Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Herefie,</hi> paralel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our new <hi>Seekers, Shakers, Lay-preachers, Leaveners, Enthuſiaſts, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, Anabaptiſts,</hi> with their predeceſſors, their <hi>Cozen-Germanes</hi> in now ruinated <hi>Germany,</hi> and with our <hi>Norfolk Ket, Hacket, Jack Cade, Tiler, Straw,</hi> and other <hi>firebrands of Rebellion</hi> at home: I cannot but <hi>dicere &amp; praedicere,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie truly (though perhaps like <hi>Chelcas and Caſſandra,</hi> not beleeved) if ever <hi>London</hi> be paſſive in blood or goods in this age, it will be, not by <hi>forreign power</hi> (for <hi>Seleuchus</hi> his rods cannot be broken ſo long as they are faſt tyed and bund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>together)</hi> but by the factions and fractions of her own home-bred, in-bred <hi>Hereſies</hi> (like a <hi>diamond</hi> cut in its own duſt) by her preſent <hi>regnant ſins,</hi> ripen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her <hi>ruine</hi> with other Nations, chiefly <hi>her preſent distractions,</hi> haſtening and hurrying on her deſtructions, <hi>Quod omen avertat Deus! Meliora ſpero, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jora timeo: Et ſerò ſapiunt Phryges: ſerò medicina paratur:</hi> which to <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</hi> what you may after <hi>repent,</hi> though I may be thought in politicals to be out of my element, even <hi>piſcis in arido,</hi> and as unfit to councel you, as once <hi>Phorimo Hannibal,</hi> Yet, <hi>ſi quid mea carmina poſſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> if my wiſhes were not in vain, I could deſire, that as you have a <hi>care</hi> in electing &amp; ſelecting of <hi>your Maiors,</hi> much more the <hi>Rectors of your Militia,</hi> leſt <hi>Militia turn</hi> into <hi>Malitia: (plus in duce quàm in exercitu.</hi>) The <hi>Athenians</hi> had <hi>a great care</hi> to truſt none with the keyes of the City but <hi>Solon,</hi> a wiſe and juſt man, for a <hi>Pagan:</hi> Oh for a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> to this City <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Si non Sinon:</hi> all is not gold that gliſters: many a nut with a fair ſhell is deaf, rotten and worm-eaten: for my part, give me the nut called the brown leamin, as moſt ſollid, maſſy, and ponderous, found in the kernel, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to be crackt in the ſhell. If any be ſuſpected, much more detected, in place and grace, with you to be looſe in the haſt, to ſhrink like ſome Weſtern cloth in the wetting, to ſide with Sectaries, to liſt whom he liſt, even Church and State-firing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:162081:7"/>
Schiſmaticks; admit not ſuch a raſh phaeton to ſit as regent: ſuch withall as the ſons of <hi>Brutus,</hi> who would keep in, or bring in, any proud and pernitious <hi>Tarquins,</hi> are to be expulſed: The very Geeſe and Ganders are not ſo unwiſe as to chuſe the Fox for their Governor, <hi>pereat unus; non unitas:</hi> Its better many Gangreend or rotten Members to be cut off, then the whole City infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: In this caſe, above any of <hi>Merlins</hi> or mother <hi>Shiptons</hi> Propheſies, the Proverb may be verified, fooliſh pitty ſpoils the City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[It was likewiſe inquired how the General had performed his word with the King and Kingdom, in re-eſtabliſhing the King, and reſtoring the Kingdom to Peace; he anſwered, the General never intended any ſuch thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did he never intend it? Did he ever acquaint this <hi>Dias</hi> with his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Sure if he had, after the curteſie of the <hi>French King</hi> to <hi>Scoggan,</hi> he had been fitter to be of his Privy, then of his Cabinet Councel; for you ſee he is <hi>rimarum plenus,</hi> a leaking veſſel full of holes; he keeps Councel as well as <hi>Scoggans wiſe,</hi> or <hi>Fabius</hi> once the divulged ſecrets of <hi>Auguſtus Coeſar;</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals what he knows of the <hi>Army,</hi> and of his <hi>General,</hi> and perhaps ten times more: (it being the Devils Arithmetick to make lyes by addition, as un juſt plunderers ſteal by ſubſtraction; and the family of Love or Luſt ſpawn ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards by multiplication:) Sure though this Souldier be no <hi>Epheſtion,</hi> yet a ſeal had need be ſet on his lips.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He did never intend it.</hi>] Into his ſecrets let not my ſoul enter; perhaps, <hi>primum in intentione ultimum in executione,</hi> what was firſt in intention, may be at laſt in ex cution: He that reads Shepards Jubilee in his <hi>encomium,</hi> were he as ſnakiſhly envious againſt his wel-deſervings, as ever any emulating Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen s againſt the famous <hi>Themiſt ocles, Alcibiad s, Miltiades,</hi> the two <hi>Scipioes,</hi> or any other renowned <hi>Martialiſts,</hi> cannot but ſay, that he hath done much fame worthy, and that God hath done much by him; yet <hi>pace tanti viti,</hi> to interpoſe my opinion, if not judgment, had be brought his King to an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view and perſonal Treaty with his Parliament, which was ſo projected, and ſo ſtrongly ſtill expected, as the moſt probable means of a ſetled Peace, (as <hi>Diſcuſſions</hi> bring forth truth and unity, as the repercuſſions of the ſteel and flint bring forth fire:) I ſay, when the ball was at his foot (as perhaps it may be again, or is) to have brought his Prince to his <hi>Peers,</hi> and as a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>Caſſander,</hi> to ſet the ſtrings that were out of tune, to thoſe that were in tune, in an <hi>Harmonious diapaſon;</hi> he had then, as wiſe men think, joyned <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſes</hi> his head to. <hi>Ajax</hi> hand, policy to proweſſe, as a pearl in gold, and for ever aeternized his name, like <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> the late famous Sweed; yea he had been held to <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Camillus</hi> and <hi>Fabius</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> the reſtorer of her to a new life; yea the <hi>Atlas</hi> mainly propping a declining ſtate.</p>
            <p>Both ſaith <hi>Dias, he did never intend it.</hi>] His General is much beholden to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:162081:8"/>
him, to brand him, to blow hot and cold, as the <hi>Satyres</hi> Hoſt with one breath, yea to ſympathize with <hi>Pope Alexander,</hi> and his good ſon <hi>Coeſar Borgias,</hi> the one of them never ſpeaking as he thought, the other never thinking as he ſpoke, (their <hi>words</hi> and <hi>works</hi> like <hi>Germans</hi> lips, as the phraſe is, being nine mile a ſunder,) theſe two, the old Fox, and the young Cub, being Matchavils, perfect patterns, and Ideas of his right moulded politick Prince; which Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chavil many <hi>Polypragmateſts</hi> have ſtudyed, more then <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that for the Perſonal Treaty, the Army would not ſuffer it.</hi>] More is the pitty, that now <hi>Gowns</hi> muſt give place to <hi>Guns;</hi> that <hi>cedant arma togae,</hi> is held no true <hi>Syntaxis,</hi> at leaſt a <hi>Pſeudodox,</hi> not an <hi>Orthodox</hi> Tenet; that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles</hi> armour is judged from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes</hi> to raſh <hi>Ajax,</hi> though leſſe worthy; yea, that any free Parliament ſhould be limited, bounded and obſtructed, like thoſe that are in a ſhip, or in a Coach, who muſt go either as the wooden Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horſe, and the Land Chariot carrieth them them, or if they leap out of the firſt, they indanger drowning, or out of the ſecond, a neck or a leg breaking, or brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Can the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> be held a free Councel, or rather a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, who (as learned and judicious Doctor <hi>Brent,</hi> in his worthy book in fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio, hath turned the inſide of it outward,) did not, nay durſt not decree any thing, but what they had from their <hi>Popes?</hi> as the moon her borrowed light from the Sun; from whence the Sarcaſm was, that the Holy Ghoſt was ever brought to them from <hi>Rome,</hi> as a Bee in a box: But why would not, or wil not, the <hi>Army</hi> ſuffer this Treaty?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Becauſe the City would think they gained the honor of it.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Would think.</hi>] Hath this Momus any windows to look into the hearts of the <hi>Citizens,</hi> what they think? Will he enter into a premunire againſt God, to be <hi>Cardiognoſes,</hi> the <hi>ſearcher of hearts?</hi> Muſt any <hi>Joſeph</hi> be above <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in the throne? He meaſures the City by his own Laſt, and makes <hi>concluſions,</hi> yea <hi>confuſions</hi> from the <hi>deluſions of his own thoughts;</hi> as we ſay in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> juſt as the fool thinketh, ſo the Bell clinketh, Come again <hi>Whittington;</hi> as for the City, as there be many things, <hi>que non niſi per acta landantur,</hi> which are not praiſe-worthy till finiſhed: So I perſwade my ſelf, the City would be glad at their hearts, of ſuch a Treaty to be the husband as would marry with Peace, as once the white Roſe with the red, in a bleſſed Union, after many bloody <hi>Combuſtions;</hi> yea, there be millions of <hi>Mephiboſheths,</hi> who prefer the <hi>Kings</hi> ſafe reducing to his <hi>Crown, Peers and People,</hi> above their own <hi>lives</hi> and <hi>liberties,</hi> and would bleſs God for any one that ſhould be that happy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to effect it; even as a ſincere Preacher with <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit is glad howſoever that the Goſpel is preached, without emulation of the Organ of the converſion of ſouls: as if a man be pulled out of the pit as <hi>Joſeph,</hi> or out of the dungeon with <hi>Jeremiah;</hi> or as a brand out of the fire, what makes matter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:162081:8"/>
who he be, whether friend or foe, that doth the good work? Let the Army do the great work, the great duty, and let them on Gods Name receive the great Dignity, the City will yeeld them the <hi>Bucklers</hi> the great <hi>Honors</hi> of <hi>Patres Patria,</hi> the <hi>Patriots</hi> of their Country: <hi>Onus et bonos, officium et beneficium</hi> ſhall both be theirs: But let us trace him further.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He would not have the City to have the honor of bringing the King to a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but the Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh what a conteſting is here about Honor? as the ſeven Cities once about <hi>Homer:</hi> the Lady <hi>Honora,</hi> and that pale-faced <hi>Pecunia,</hi> like the <hi>Corinthian Lais,</hi> is Courted of all in <hi>Cities, Courts</hi> and <hi>Camps;</hi> all would ſhine in the Orb of Honor; moſt in any place or office, would like <hi>Coeſar</hi> have no equals; or like <hi>Pompey</hi> no <hi>Superiors;</hi> all would be <hi>aut Caſares, ant nihil Caſars</hi> or nothing, Kings even of molehils: How innate it is to the nature of all, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of <hi>Artiſts</hi> and <hi>Martialiſts,</hi> to emulate rather the <hi>Honors</hi> and <hi>Dignities,</hi> then imitate the deſerts of others! as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> cannot ſleep for the envied <hi>Trophies</hi> of <hi>Miltiades,</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> weeps at the Tomb of <hi>Achilles,</hi> ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſed by the Muſe of a <hi>Homer. O doxa, doxa,</hi> oh glory, glory, cries the <hi>Orator,</hi> how doſt thou boyl in the hearts of men? Oh how the honor of men hath been, and is aymed at by ſuch Souldiers as <hi>Dias,</hi> and his camped <hi>fellows,</hi> more then the Glory of God? <hi>Immenſum gloria calcar babet:</hi> Oh what a ſpur hath this vain-glory, to be the ſubject of a ſtory! This is the whetſtone to the <hi>Decians, Horatians, Scipioes, Codrus, Timoleon, Anstogiton, Scevola,</hi> and millions moe of all other <hi>Heriock acts,</hi> not ſo much undergone for the love of their Country, as for the luſt of vain-glory: For this purchaſe <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> makes his way through the <hi>Alpes, Ceſar</hi> pitcheth ſo main <hi>battails,</hi> the three <hi>Herods,</hi> our <hi>Richard</hi> the third, and thouſand moe, ſwim to <hi>Crowns</hi> through <hi>Hecatombs</hi> and <hi>Seas</hi> of blood: the <hi>Aegyptian Kings</hi> build their <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramides, Abſolon</hi> rears a <hi>Pillar,</hi> and every man doth ſomething, from the Court to the Cart, for this aery bubble, this windy blather, this vulgar vote, this Plebeian puff, called honor. Some in the Army you ſee (if <hi>Dias</hi> be not <hi>Monſieur Mendax,</hi>) will croſs the publike good of a Kingdom in reducing the King, rather then the City ſhould monopolize this poor Punctillio of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor from them, on which they ſtand ſo much; as on their tiptoes; as many Victories have been obſtructed, many Battails loſt, many Armies routed, yea often Expeditions of Chriſtian <hi>Princes</hi> againſt the <hi>Turk</hi> annihilated, (as I could bring in a Cloud of <hi>Histories,</hi>) meerly by the wild-fire <hi>Emulations</hi> of <hi>commanders</hi> about the <hi>Honors</hi> of ſeveral <hi>ſervices:</hi> Oh that as <hi>Iordan</hi> was turned bickward, we could turn the ſtream of our <hi>boundleſs ambitions</hi> after <hi>humane Honors,</hi> meerly to the Honor and Glory of God: then in a good Cauſe ſhould the ſwords of our <hi>Martialiſts,</hi> like the ſwords of <hi>Ionathan</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:162081:9"/>
               <hi>Saul.</hi> return gloriouſly with the blood of the ſlain, if, with <hi>David and Jaſhuah,</hi> they ſought the Lords battels and not their own, ſought his honor, not their own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[And that the Parliament did vote the Perſonal Treaty only to delude the people.</hi>] But how knows he this? hath he ſome <hi>Mephiſtophiles</hi> like <hi>Faustus,</hi> ſome familiar ſpirit, as ſome <hi>Italian,</hi> in a ring; ſome devil, like <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> in the form of a dog: or ſome lylng ſpirits like <hi>Ahabs</hi> prophets, to acquaint him with this; or is it his own mad imagination (or, as the Country-man miſ. called it, <hi>madg-maſon;</hi>) but till he prove this, what ſlit deſerves the ſcandalizing tongue of this reviling <hi>Shimei,</hi> this railing <hi>Rabſhekah:</hi> if <hi>ſcandalum magnatum,</hi> in ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering one noble man, be ſo poenal, what is it for this whelp of <hi>Cerberus,</hi> to bite with his <hi>Theonine</hi> teeth a whole Parliament; for this <hi>malevolent</hi> to caſt his ſoul aſperſions on ſo many ſelected Senators throughout the Kingdom? but mens tongues are now more then ever their own: what Law, yea what Lord can controul them, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 12. this were to tame <hi>Panthers,</hi> and to ſhackle the <hi>Helleſpont</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[He likewiſe ſaid, <hi>He ſhould (or hoped) to ſee the City on fire ſhortly.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Yet more fire, more ire: ſtill the ſame <hi>Arminian Dragon</hi> ſpitting fire! <hi>At dabit Deus his quoque funem:</hi> God will caſt on ſuch a ſpirit <hi>lightening and thunder, ſtorm and tempeſt, fire and hail,</hi> Pſa. II. <hi>Satia te ſanguine quem ſatiſti. Neſtorius</hi> tongue that fired that world was ſcorched in his mouth: <hi>Valens</hi> that fired ſo many Chriſtians, was at laſt fired by the <hi>Gothes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[But he hopes to ſee it fired.</hi>] His is ſuch a hope as will never help him to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; it will melt as ſnow to dirt, and periſh with himſelf, as an <hi>embrio,</hi> or the graſs on the houſe top, which withereth. Oh the poor hopes of the wicked (like the Romanized Religion) founded in blood and watered with blood!</p>
            <p>[He further ſaid, <hi>That if the Kings revenue were ten times ſo much the more, in were the better for them, for the Crown Land would make many of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers Gentlemen.</hi>] And ſo indeed it would make not only <hi>Jack,</hi> but <hi>Jackie</hi> too, a Gentleman, if he had the conſcience to purſe it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this windy-bags venting, <hi>That if they conquer us, we ſhall be their ſlaves, even ſlaves to ſuch as he, as Sicilian</hi> Lords once were oppoſed by their ſervants, <hi>Soepe bilem, ſoepeque riſum veſtri movere tumultus:</hi> the humor of this fellow perſonating that bragging <hi>Thraſo</hi> in <hi>Terence,</hi> and <hi>Peripolinices</hi> in <hi>Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias,</hi> and of <hi>Bragauacheo</hi> in <hi>Spencers Fairy Queen;</hi> I know not whether I ſhould laugh at him, pity him, or be angry with him. Thus having in this Rapſody ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered ſome grapes of political obſervances from his thorns, and ſome gold of good counſels from his droſs, I ſheath my pen from running any further Tilt with the pike of his tongue, having unhorſſed (though not un-aſſed) him enough al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, for abuſing, as a bold Buffoon, even his own Army, as well as King, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Parliament.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Downame;</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July. the 26. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
